Guide to the Frederick E. (Frederick Edward) Brasch Papers, 1745-1963
Department of Special Collections
Frederick E. (Frederick Edward) Brasch Papers,
1745-1963
Special Collections M0275
Brasch, Frederick E. (Frederick Edward), 1875-1967.
65 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift of the Brasch family, 1967 and 1987.
Biographical Note
Frederick Edward Brasch was born December 18, 1875, the son of Otto Wilhelm and Carolyn E. (Johannsen). He attended Stanford University from 1897-1899; Univ. of California, 1899-1901, Harvard, 1916. On August 5, 1903 he married Winnifred E. Orpin (who died June 11, 1938). The marriage produced two children, Carolyn Mildred and Maxwell Frederick.
The following is a list of F. E. Brasch's occupations
Asst. observer, Harvard College Observatory, 1903-1904.
Computer, Lick Observatory, Mt. Hamilton, CA. 1905
Asst. at Stanford Library, 1912-16.
Asst. reference librarian, John Cresar Library, Chicago. 1917-21.
Reference librarian, James Jerome Hill Reference Library, St. Paul, Minn. 1921-22
Bibliographic research, National Research Council, Wash., D.C. 1922-3.
Librarian, Dept. of Terrestrial Magnetism, carnegie Institution, Wash. 1923-4
Secretary of the history of science section, A.A.A.S. 1920-28.
Secretary of Isaac Newton commemoration, 192-
Chief of Scientific Collection, Library of congress. 1925-43.
Consultant in history of science, 1944-8.
Consultant in bibliography, Stanford Univ., 1948-67.
The following is a list of F. E. Brasch's associations:
American Assn for the Advancement of Science
Royal Astronomical Society
History of Science Society
International Astronomical Union
Astronomical Society of the Pacific
American Astronomical Society
American Antiquarian Society
Phi Beta Kappa
Sigma Xi
Unitarian Church
In 1941, on the occasion of the fiftieth anniversary of Stanford University, F. E. Brasch donated his entire Newton Collection to the University, in gratitude for the opportunity of pursuing scientific astronomical studies there (1897-9).
Frederich Brasch died on October 26, 1967.
Scope and Content
Correspondence and manuscript notes of Brasch and article reprints, photographs, and memorabilia collected by Brasch on the history of science in general and the history of astronomy from Isaac Newton to the modern period.
Arrangement
The boxes of manuscript material are arranged roughly according to subject:
Boxes 2-8. Colonial Science: general
Boxes 9-13. Colonial Science: John Winthrop and the colonial Newtonists
Boxes 14-23. Isaac Newton and his contemporaries
Boxes 24-25. Albert Einstein
Boxes 26-35. T. J. J. See (Navy astronomey; opposed to Einstein's Theory of relativity)
Boxes 36-38. Lick Observation
Boxes 39-54. FEB and his involvement in science: articles, societies, projects, scientist acquaintances
Boxes 55-72. Card catologues (prepared by FEB)
Boxes 73-76. FEB and the Library of Congress
Boxes 77-78. Science catalogs and bills for individual items of Newton collection
Boxes 79-86. FEB correspondence: specific parties
Boxes 87-95. FEB correspondence: misc.
Boxes 96-97. FEB memorabilia
Boxes 98-99. College catalogues
Boxes 100-102. Studies in English literature and philology
Box 1 contains a miscellaneous assortment of gems extrated from the collection in August, 1975. Because there were no references as to the original location of the individual items within the collection as a whole, they remain separate, a hodge-podge of items of widely varying significance ranging from the 17th to the 20th centuries.
All other gems which I have found within the collection remain there, and are indicated by an asterisk (*) preceding the item's description.
The catagories of manuscripts listed above are anything but representative of every item within a given subset. The original integrity within the individual boxes has been generally respected, except in cases where the contents clearly have no reasonable order. In this situation I have relocated material according to the afore mentioned subject guidelines.
Catalogued during the academic year of 1980/81 by Kenneth B. Wolf Dept. of History
Container List
- Collection gems (extracted 8/75) (Box 1)
  - Sewall, Stephen, An Oration Delivered at the Funeral of the Hon. John Winthrop. Boston, 1779., (printed) (Box-folder B1, F1)
  - Winthrop, James.
    An Attempt to settle the magnitude of the Solar System and the distance of the fixed stars. AMsS, n.d.
    Geometric Method of Finding mean proportionals, AMsI, n.d.
    James Winthrop, 1781 autograph signature.
  - Acta Eruditorium. reviews of Newton, Leibniz, etc. n.d.
  - Stiles, Ezra (1727-1795; president of Yale)
    Miscellaneous notes & mathematical calculations re: comets, transit of Mercury, Aurora Borealis, 1745-1784. Mss different hands.
  - Atwater, Noah, (senior tutor at Yale)
  - Copernicus, Nicolaus. Copy of engraving, 1654.
  - Pierce, Benjamin. (Harvard Math. Prof., fl. 1850's) (Box-folder B1, F2)
    ALS Pierce to a colleague. Cambridge 1854.
    Photo of Pierce.
  - Bowditch, Nathaniel
    Addition to the memoir on the Solar Eclipse of June 16, 1806. AMs S.
    Observations on the total eclipse of the Sun of June 16, 1806 mode at Salem. AMs S.
    Observations of the Comet - 1807 AMs S..
    Chapter II: On the figure of the earth, AMs S.
    ALS Bowditch to Rev. Joseph Williard. Salem, 1797.
    Engraving of Bowditch (1838) from H. I. Bowditch's biography of his father.
  - Perkins, George R. ALS Perkins to N. Bowditch. Boston, 1838.
  - Hassler, Ferdinand.
    ALS Hassler to Leo Woodbury, Secy. of the Treasury. Washington, 1839.
    ALS Hassler to Walter Forward, Secy. of the Treasury. Washington 1842.
    ANS Hassler to Secy. of of the Treasury, Washington, 1842
  - Newcomb, Simon (1835-1909)
    Announcement lectures at John Hopkins University on history of astronomy, 1876-77.
    Outline of a direct and easy method of affecting the development of the pertubative function and its differential coefficient AMs
    Fragmentary lecture notes, AMs
    Engraved portrait Photo
  - Young, C.A. (Dartmouth) ALS Young to S. Newcomb 1876
  - Kelvin (Lord) [Sir William Thomas]. AI. C.W. Siemens / with kind regards/ W.T. / Southampton Aug. 27, 1882.
  - Unidentified Ms found by FEB in purchased copy of Davidis Gregorii... Astronomiae.... Geneva, 1726.
  - American Academy of Sciences. Founding articles, Aug 15, 1865., Photocopy (Box-folder B1, F3)
  - Boyle, R.O. Several letters to/from. 1679-85., Photocopy.
  - The First Book of Euclid's Elements, Photocopy.
    folio 8-12.
  - Misc photocopies of 18 th c printed matter.
  - Rouse-Ball, W. W. Newton's Principles., TMs w/annot. 23 pp. (Box-folder B1, F4)
  - Russell, Bertrand. Application card to History of Science Society. Approved 4/20/27 by FEB.
  - Poincare, Excerpts from address on the future of mathematics. 1908., TMs 2 pp.
  - Holden, Edwards. (Lick Observatory) Memorandum on the Preparation of a Catalogue from the Washington Zones, 1846-50. Lick Obs., 1896., AMsS 3 pp.
  - Erick, John Francis (1791 -).Biographical article (fragment)., Printed
  - Lecat, Maurice (C. E. Louvain) Business card w/annot. 1924
  - Cajori, Florian (univ. of Calif., Berkeley) A Century of American Geodesy HSS mtg, Durham, 1929., TMS of intro., 1 p.
  - Eliot, C. W., TLS 9/28/20 CWE (Mainc) to FEB re: B.Pierce.
  - Whitmore, James ALS 2/22/20 JW (New Haven) to FEB ve: B. Pierce.
  - Johnson (Senator) Ms draft of statement re: Naval observatory deterioration of standards [1948?]Fragment., 1 p.
  - de Bois-Raymond, Paul. Extract of an address at Tubingen 1874., 3 pp. w/annot.
- Colonial Science: general (Box 2)
  (not divided into folders)
  FEB notes (AMs/TMs) intended for lecture, publication, or personal use, re: history of colonial Scientific thought, esp. as it relates to Newton. Includes studies re:
  John Winthrop
  Cotton Mathev
  Increase Mathev
  Early astronomical & mathematical work at Harvard and William and Mary.
- Colonial Science: general (Box 3)
  - FEB notes (AMs/TMs) re: (Box-folder B3, F1)
    Science at Colonial Harvard
    Newton
  - FEB notes (AMs/TMs) re: (Box-folder B3, F2)
    Colonial surveying and navigation as applied Science
    Newtonian Scientific influence
    Science and the colonial mind
    Political philosophy of the Declaration of Independence
    17th c. Science & research at Wilham and Mary.
  - FEB notes and drafts for articles (AMs/TMs) re: early science at Yale and Columbia (King's College) (Box-folder B3, F3)
    article re: W.S. Johnson, first pres. of Columbia.
    notes re: Science at colonial yale
    notes re: Ezra Stiles, 18thc Yale Newtonian. (see E. S. Mss, Box 1)
    notes articles re: Samuel Johnson, 18th c. pres. of King's College.
  - Matter re: Isaac Greenwood, 18th c Harvard mathematician (Box-folder B3, F4)
    I.G. A Philosophical Discourse concerning the Mutability changes of the Material World. 1731. (photostat)
    I.G. correspondence (photostat)
  - FEB notes (AMs/TMs) re: Newtonian epoch of colonial science: mathematics from 1636-1738.FEB article, The Newtonian Epoch in the American Colonies (Box-folder B3, F5)
  - FEB note (AMs/TMs) re: Winthrop study of the transits of Mercury and Venus (1740-1769) (Box-folder B3, F6)
  - Matter re: Count Rumford (1753-1814),American Scientist (Box-folder B3, F7)
  - FEB notes (AMs) re: (Box-folder B3, F8)
    History of nationalism & experimentism
    J. Winthrop and colonial scientific Thought, esp. at Harvard
    Colonial almanacs
    Cotton Mather
    Thomas Robie (1689-1729)
- Colonial Science: general (Box 4)
  - Matter re: Cadwallader Colden (1769-1834), biographer and friend of Robert Fulton (Box-folder B4, F1)
    Autographed copy of Philosophical Transactions, 1714.
    Page from the Transactors of the Royal Society of London, v. 49 (1755) w/ CC's letter to P. Collinson describing earthquake in N. Y. (Nov. 13, 1755).
    Photostats of other letters from CC to Collinson.
    Misc. articles and notes re: CC.
    Ms description of CC's Ms copy book.
  - Matter re: science in New York colony page from New York Chronical (1769)diagram of Venus' transit.
  - Bowdoin, James. ALS (1764)describing and illustrating telescope improvements, (photostat). (Box-folder B4, F2)
  - FEB notes (AMs/TMs) re: colonial Science, particularly Harvard's role. (Box-folder B4, F3)
  - Articles re: Jeremiah Horrox (1619-1641)minister and astronomer. (Box-folder B4, F4)
- Colonial science: matter re: Thomas Jefferson (Box 5)
  - Misc. articles about Jefferson, including FEB's, Thomas Jefferson, the Scientist. (Box-folder B5, F1)
  - a) Transcriptions and photostats of some Jefferson letters (Box-folder B5, F2-3)
  - b) FEB notes (AMs) re: Jefferson
  - c) FEB correspondence re:
    various Jeffersonian functions
    acquisition of Jefferson materials
  - * Copy of a Jefferson portrait (Box-folder B5, F4)
- Colonial Science: matter re: George Washington (Box 6)
  - Misc. articles, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, reproductions of pictures (Box-folder B6, F1-2)
  - FEB notes (AMs/TMs) re: Washington as a scientist. (Box-folder B6, F3)
  - Matter re: the city of Washington (Box-folder B6, F4-5)
    tour pamphlets
    articles re: planning & building
  - Journal of American History 4: 1 (1910) (Box-folder B6, F6)
    containing reproductions of revolutionary period art.
- Colonial Science: matter re: Benjamin Franklin (Box 7)
  - Misc. articles, photostats of letters, photos of Franklin's scientific equipment, FEB correspondence re: acquisition of Franklin materials. (Box-folder B7, F1-2)
- Colonial Science: matter re: Massachusetts history (Box 8)
  - Misc. articles & booklets (Box-folder B8, F1)
  - a) Lodge, H.C. The Pilgrims of Plymouths. (1921) (Box-folder B8, F2)
  - b) Towne, E.C. Studies in Pilgrim History (1905)
  - Misc. articles & clippings re: Harvard (Box-folder B8, F3)
  - a) Matter re: Joseph Lovering (1813-1892), American Scientist. (Box-folder B8, F4)
  - b) Boston & Science
- Colonial Science: John Winthrop (1714-1779) and the colonial Newtonists (Box 9)
  - Matter re: FEB's article, The Royal Society of London & its Influence upon Scientific Thought in the American Colonies. (Box-folder B9, F1-3)
    drafts (FEB AMs/TMs)
    related articles
    related correspondence
  - Matter re: a science text (AMs) written by Chas. Morton (Colonial Harvard Scientist) (Box-folder B9, F4)
    correspondence re: location of Ms.
    FEB transcription of parts of text.
  - a) FEB notes (AMs/TMs) re: early Harvard tutor (Box-folder B9, F5)
  - b) Matter re: celestial almanacs: notes and lists.
  - FEB transcription (AMs/TMs) of earliest know catalogue of Harvard library, 1764 (Box-folder B9, F6)
  - FEB correspondence re: acquisition of Winthrop (Box-folder B9, F7-8)
- Colonial Science: John Winthrop and the colonial Newtonists (Box 10)
  - FEB drafts (AMs/TMs) of various books & articles re: John Winthrop & David Rittenhos (Box-folder B10, F1-2)
    The Mathematical Studies of J.W.
    America's first Astronomer, J.W.
    Life & Work of J.W.
    The History of Astronomy in America
    David Rittenhouse (1732-1796) & the American Philosophical Society.
    Notes & Impressions relating to the Tercentenary Celebration of the Birth of Isaac Newton
  - FEB drafts (AMs/TMs) of America's First Astronomer & the Science of his period, J.W. (1714-1779). (Box-folder B10, F3)
  - FEB draft (AMs) of History of Astronomy in America (Box-folder B10, F4)
  - FEB drafts (TMs) of Medical Men in Mathematics, Astronomy, & Physics. (Box-folder B10, F5)
  - a) Misc. articles re: J.W. (Box-folder B10, F6)
  - b) transcription of J.W.'s, Lecture on Earthquake
  - a) correspondence re: an FEB Winthrop article primarily critiques (Box-folder B10, F7)
  - b) misc. correspondence W/ Phi Beta Kappa
  - c) photos of scientific instruments
  - FEB notes re: article, Brown University & Benjamin West (Colonial astronemer). (Box-folder B10, F8)
- Colonial Science: John Winthrop & the colonial Newtons (Box 11)
  - Photostats of printed J.W. matter. (Box-folder B11, F1)
    Aberration & Transit of Venus (1769)
    Observations of the Transit of Venus [1765] 2 articles
    Observations of the Transit of Mercury (17--) 2 articles
    Remarks upon a passage in Castilliano's Life of Sir Isaac Newton (1773)
    Correspondence: John Adams & J. W. (1775)
  - Photostats of printed J.W. matter. (Box-folder B11, F2)
    An Account of a Meteor (1760)
    An Account of an Earthquake... (1755)
    Transit of Mercury (1742)
    Letter to the Boston Gazette (1756)
    Letter from Cromwell Mortimer to J.W. (1741)
  - Articles & notes re: colonial science (esp. J.W.), Puritans. (Box-folder B11, f3-4)
  - Matter re: J.W. & colonial science (Box-folder B11, F5)
    FEB notes
    newsclippings
    book catalogues
    photos of J.W. descendents, grave, scientific apparatus
  - * a) J.W. AMss. (Box-folder B11, F6)
  - b) FEB notes
  - a) FEB notes (AMs/TMs) re: (Box-folder B11, F7)
    J.W. & colonial science in general
    History of Astronomy in America
  - b) Misc. articles re: J.W., early colonial chemists medicine.
  - c) articles (TMs) by C.A. Browne re: J.W.
  - * d) Observations of the solar eclipse of Sept. 17 1811by John Fran.
- Colonial Science: John Winthrop & the Colonial Newtonists (Box 12)
  - Photostats: (Box-folder B12, F1)
    early printed copy of Euclid
    correspondence of John Clayton, Cadwatha Colden
  - FEB drafts (TMss) of The History of Astronomy in America: 1621-1783 (Box-folder B12, F2-3)
  - FEB drafts (AMs/TMs) of various works be colonial science, esp. JW (Box-folder B12, F4-5)
  - FEB drafts (AMs/TMs) of article, History of Harvard Observatory. Other drafts of articles are: modern science, books review (Box-folder B12, F6)
  - Matter re: David Ritten house: (Box-folder B12, F7)
    articles
    matter pertaining to functions of Ritten house Society
  - Matter re: David Ritten house (1732-96): (Box-folder B12, F8)
    FEB draft (TMs) of article, D. R. & his contemporaries in The Royal Society of London.
    article from Science News Letter, 1932
    matter re: Walter Minto, math. prof. at Princeton (1787-96: contemporary of Rittenhouse).
    FEB notes (AMs)
    photostats of letters
    Minto Ms Leaf
- Colonial Science: John Winthrop & The Colonial Newtonists John Winthrops LL.D: 1714-1779. Professor of Mathematics & Natural Philosophy, Harvard College, 1738-1779. Folio scrapbook compiled by FEB (1932),containing articles, photos, photostats related to JW. (Box 13)
- Isaac Newton: the influence of the Principia (Box 14)
  - a) Matter re: FEB's article on James Logan, colonial mathematician & the first to bring Newton's Principia to the colonies. (Box-folder B14, F1)
  - b) Matter re: David Rittenhouse & John Ewing.
  - Matter re: FEB's attempts to determine provenance of an annotated copy of the Principia, located at William & Mary. Primarily correspondence. (Box-folder B14, F2)
  - a) Results of FEB's research re: the William & Mary Principia in the form of notes for lectures. (Box-folder B14, F3-4)
  - b) Matter re: location of all copies of Principia in America.
  - Matter re: FEB's tracking down of an Australian copy of the Principia. Correspondence & Photostats. (Box-folder B14, F5-6)
- Isaac Newton (1642-1727): Bicentenary (of his Death) 1927: (Box 15)
  - FEB drafts (AMs/TMs) of lecture delivered at bicentenary: John Winthrop: America's First Astronomer & the First Critical disciple of Sir Isaac Newton in the Colonies. (Box-folder B15, F1)
  - Matter re: Bicentenary (Box-folder B15, F2-4)
    programs
    announcements
    plans
    FEB's address
  - FEB correspondence re: Bicentenary, re: (Box-folder B15, F5)
    securing participant lecturers
    publication of the bicentenary lectures
  - FEB correspondence w/ the Williams & Wilkins Company, publishers of FEB's edited work, Sir Isaac Newton, stemming from the bicentenary. (Box-folder B15, F6)
  - a) FEB correspondence primarily re: acquisition of Newton material. (Box-folder B15, F7)
  - * b) reprint of Newton etching, 1831.
- Isaac Newton & his contemporaries (Box 16)
  - Matter re: Newton Tercentenary (of his birth) celebrated by Royal Society in 1946, &attended by FEB. (Box-folder B16, F1-3)
    clippings
    corresponce
  - FEB notes (AMs/TMs) on Newtonian topics, perhaps from Tercentenary. (Box-folder B16, F4)
  - Matter re: correspondence of Newton and Edmond Halley, compiled by Eugene Fairfield MacPike. Bibliography, articles, (TMs), and photostats of letters. (Box-folder B16, F5)
  - Matter re: Mss of Alexander M. Fisher's Study of Gravitation at Yale College, 1815-1822. (Box-folder B16, F6)
    photostats of Fisher Mss. Selected pages from the William & Mary copy of Principia.
    FEB correspondence w/ Yale library re: Fisher Mss.
  - a) FEB notes (AMs) re: Robert Boyle's Sceptical Chemist (1661, 1680 editions). (Box-folder B16, F7)
  - b) book lists: Newton & Kepler works. FEB correspondence w/ dealers
  - c) short reviews of FEB's compilation of Newton portraits
  - d) FEB correspondence re: H. W. Robinson's The Diary of Robert Hooke... 1672-1680,primarily btwn FEB and Eugene F. MacPike
  - e) FEB notes (AMs) re: Newton's early years
  - f) FEB draft of letter describing his Newton Collection (1960)
  - Misc. photostats of: (Box-folder B16, F8)
    a portion of biography of Benjamin West (1738-1820).
    a letter from a John Winthrop, Jr. to his son at Harvard, 1672.
    description of picture of Winthrop's transit instrument (no picture here).
- Isaac Newton and his forbears (Box 17)
  - Matter re: FEB's proposal for translation of S. I. Vavilov's biography of Isaac Newton, including typed copy of portion of that translation (Box-folder B17, F1)
  - Misc. matter re: Newton (also Galileo, Kepler, Bacon) (Box-folder B17, F2-3)
    newspaper & magazine clippings
    catalogues of Newtonia
    programs & announcements for exhibition
  - * Selection of 18th, 19th, & 20th century encycloped articles re: Newton (Box-folder B17, F4)
  - Matter re: Edmond Halley (Box-folder B17, F5)
    British reviews of Engene F. Mac Pike's, correspondence & Papers of Edmond Halley
    articles by Mac Pike re: E. Halley
  - Matter re: Roger Bacon (Box-folder B17, F6)
    misc. articles
  - Articles (TMs) by Raymond J. Seeger (Box-folder B17, F7)
    Galilco Pilgrimage
    On the Role of Galileo in Physics
    Imperatives for Peace
  - Draft (TMs) of Johan Kepler (1571-1630), a Tercentenary Commemoration of his Life & Work. A series of papers prepared under the auspices of the History of Science Society. (Box-folder B17, F8)
  - Bibliography of J. Kepler on index cards (Box-folder B17, F9)
  - Misc. matter (Box-folder B17, F10)
- Isaac Newton & the History of Science (Box 18)
  (not divided into folders) FEB notes (AMs) re: Newton & history of science in general, from Greck to modern times. Highly disordered.
- Isaac Newton & the History of Science (Box 19)
  FEB notes (AMs) re: Newton & history of science in general. Highly disordered.
- Isaac Newton & the History of Science (Box 20)
  Misc articles, FEB notes (AMs/TMs) & papers re: history of science
- Isaac Newton and Science in the 17th & 18th century (Box 21)
  - Matter re: FEB's bibliographical projects re: Newton & the Principia. (Box-folder B21, F1-2)
    correspondence & articles by Henry P. Macomber
  - Drafts (AMs/TMs) of FEB's address: Henry Zeitlinger (1871-1860) & Newton's Library. (Box-folder B21, F3)
  - Misc. articles re: Newton including fascimile of a Philosophical Transactions article by Newton (1672), New Theory about Light & Colors (Box-folder B21, F4)
  - Photostats of misc. Newton Mss (Box-folder B21, F5)
  - Matter re: historical eclipses (Box-folder B21, F6)
    Fotheringham, J.K. Historical Eclipses (1921)
    Hodgson, J. Account of some Eclipses (photostat of 1704 edition)
    photostat of Ms providing figures re: eclipse of 1707.
    Cushing, Harvey. An Eclipse Observed over Two Centuries Ago. (1925)
  - McCollex, Grant. The Seventeenth Century Doctrine of a Plurality of Worlds. (TMs). (Box-folder B21, F7)
- Isaac Newton: misc. (Box 22)
  - Photostats of Mss by & about Newton (Box-folder B22, F1-2)
  - Photostats of misc. Mss, including: (Box-folder B22, F3)
    Jefferson - Franklin correspondence
    William Currie Mss.
  - FEB articles, (printed): (Box-folder B22, F4)
    Report of The...Bicentenary of The Death of Sir Isaac Newton.
    The Royal Society of London & its Influence...
    Rufus Lot Green (Stanford Math. Prof., d. 1932)
    Sir William Herschel, 1738 - 1822
    Report of the Work Accomplished in the Various Libraries & Scientific Institutions of London, Cambridge, & Oxford from July 14 to Aug. 20, 1932
  - Newton bibliography, (printed & TMs) (Box-folder B22, F5)
- Isaac Newton / Albert Einstein (Box 23)
  - Misc. Newton matter, primarily re: Newton's home (Box-folder B23, F1)
    newspaper article
    magazine articles
    photostat of articles
  - Photostats of Newton Mss re: music (Box-folder B23, F2)
  - Photostats of Newton's optical lectures (Box-folder B23, F3)
  - Newton portrait negatives (Box-folder B23, F4)
  - Einstein portraits (Box-folder B23, F5)
- Albert Einstein (Box 24)
  - a) FEB correspondence re: proposed relativity bibliography (Box-folder B24, F1)
  - Matter re: theory of relativity (Box-folder B24, F2-5)
    Einstein obituaries
- Albert Einstein (Box 25)
  - Misc Matter re: Einstein & Abbe G Le Maitre (mentor of the Big Bang theory of the creation of universe) (Box-folder B25, F1-3)
- Thomas Jefferson Jackson See (Navy astronomer) (Box 26)
  - a) biographical sketch of T.J.J. See (printing) (Box-folder B26, F1)